Welcome back to Cambium Academy.
This is Course 2, Prompting Essentials.
Last week you learned what these AI models are.
This week you learn how to talk to them, because here is the strange truth:
the same AI that gives your friend brilliant answers will give you mediocre ones,
and the difference is not talent, it is technique.
In about ninety minutes you will have that technique.
You will write requests that work on the first try, and, just as important,
you will know when to trust the answer and when to check it.
Free, no signup, and a certificate when you pass the quiz.
Same promise as last week.
You need no programming, no technical background, and no particular AI app, because everything here works in ChatGPT,
Claude, Gemini, or whatever chatbot you already have open.
If you have ever typed a question into one of them and thought, hmm,
that answer was fine but not great, you are exactly who I made this for.
A browser, about ninety minutes, and zero dollars.
That is the whole entry fee.
Here is the deal we are making.
By the end, you can structure a request so it lands on the first try.
You can choose between the fast mode and the thinking mode on purpose instead of by accident.
You can control tone and format by showing an example.
You can pull honest answers out of a system that is trained to sound confident.
You can hand the AI your own documents the right way,
and you can see and edit what it remembers about you.
And you can check any answer in about sixty seconds.
Six skills.
Ninety minutes.
Let's go.
The route is the same one that worked last week.
Watch this lecture, six short modules.
Then the flashcards and the hands-on AI Lab unlock the quiz.
Twenty questions, you need fourteen, and your certificate prints on the spot.
No account, no email, no payment.
One suggestion before you start: open your favorite chatbot in another tab right now.
This is a doing course, and you will want to try things the moment you see them.
Module one.
Before we fix your prompts, I want to fix a belief.
Most people think there is a secret vocabulary, magic words that unlock the good answers,
and that power users are just people who memorized them.
That was half true in 2023.
It is not true now.
But there is one switch most people have never touched, and it changes everything.
Let me show you what actually matters in 2026.
In 2023, prompting was a treasure hunt.
People traded lists of magic phrases, and some genuinely worked, because early models were brittle.
Today's models are far better at understanding ordinary language, so the treasure hunt is over.
But here is what people get wrong:
they hear "prompt engineering is dead" and conclude that nothing they type matters.
Also false.
What died is the trick vocabulary.
What survived, and what this course teaches, is structure: what you ask for, what background you give,
and what shape you want back.
Think less secret password, more good briefing.
Here is the mental model that will carry you through this whole course.
The AI is a brilliant intern.
It has read almost everything humanity ever published, and it is fast, tireless, and eager.
But it is the intern's first day.
It does not know who you are, who the work is for, what you already tried,
or what good looks like to you.
And unless you use the memory features we will meet in Module 5,
every new chat is another first day.
So when an answer disappoints you, ask yourself the manager's question: did I brief this intern well,
or did I just bark a topic at them?
Almost everything in the next hour is learning to brief well.
Now the switch.
Every major chatbot in 2026 has two speeds.
There is an instant mode, which answers in a second or two and is perfect for everyday questions.
And there is a thinking mode, where the model works through the problem privately before it answers,
which can take from seconds to minutes.
In ChatGPT you will see Instant and Thinking in the model picker.
Claude now decides for itself how hard to think, and Gemini gives you thinking levels you can raise.
The labels move around from month to month, so do not memorize buttons.
Memorize the idea: two speeds, and you are allowed to choose.
So when do you flip it?
Stay on instant for the everyday stuff: quick facts, rewrites, brainstorming, casual back and forth.
Switch to thinking for anything where being right matters more than being fast: real math,
a plan with dependencies, comparing options, tricky logic.
Here is my rule of thumb.
If you would give a human colleague ten quiet minutes to work on it,
give the AI the thinking mode.
Most disappointing answers to hard questions are not the AI being dumb.
They are a hard question asked at the wrong speed.
Module two, the heart of the course.
I am going to show you the three parts of a request that works: the task, the context,
and the format.
Three parts, no jargon, and you already know how to do all three,
because it is exactly how you would brief a person.
Then, at the end of this module, I need to correct a famous piece of advice.
Including a piece of it that I gave you myself last week.
Part one, the task.
The single most common mistake is typing a topic, like you are still using a search engine.
"Marketing plan for a bakery" is a topic.
The model has to guess everything: how long, for whom, for what kind of bakery.
Now look at the after version.
Write, that is the verb.
A one-page marketing plan, that is the deliverable.
A neighborhood bakery targeting families within two miles, that is the audience.
Under five hundred dollars a month, that is the limit.
Same number of seconds to type, wildly better answer.
Give it a job, not a topic.
Part two, context.
Remember, it is the intern's first day.
It cannot know your dad is a retired teacher with
a dry sense of humor unless you say so.
Look at the difference.
"Write a birthday message" gets you a greeting card written for nobody in particular.
The after version gets you something that sounds like it came from his actual kid.
When you brief, answer the questions a thoughtful person would ask: who is this for,
what is the situation, what have I already tried, what does good look like here?
Two or three sentences of context routinely does more than any clever wording ever could.
Part three, format.
If you do not say what the answer should look like, the model picks for you,
and its default is that bullet-heavy, slightly corporate voice you can smell from across the room.
So say it.
Three plain sentences, no bullet points.
A table with one row per option.
Under a hundred and fifty words, in the tone of a friendly text.
Format is the cheapest instruction you can give: one short phrase at the end of your ask,
and the answer arrives already shaped like the thing you actually needed.
Here is the whole recipe on one slide, and yes, this one is worth a screenshot.
Task: what you want made.
Context: what it cannot guess.
Format: what the result should look like.
Read the example and notice it is not clever.
There is no secret phrase in it anywhere.
It is just a complete briefing, the kind you would give a smart intern on their first morning.
That is the entire modern art of prompting: say what you want, say what it needs to know,
say what it should look like.
Everything else in this course builds on this slide.
Now the correction, and this one surprised nearly everyone, including me.
The most repeated prompting tip on the internet is to start with a persona:
you are a world-class expert, act as a veteran analyst.
In 2026, researchers finally tested this properly, and here is what they found.
On tasks about facts, math, and precise recall, expert personas made accuracy slightly worse, not better.
In one study, a broad knowledge test dropped from about seventy-two percent to
about sixty-eight percent the moment a persona was added.
The best explanation: you switched the model into sound-like-an-expert mode, and sounding expert competes with being accurate.
Last week I told you the four moves included giving the AI a role.
I owe you the 2026 update: the role move is real, but it is for voice,
not for facts.
Let me show you when it still shines.
So here is the honest two-sided rule, because personas are not useless, they are mis-marketed.
When the job is about how something is said, a role works beautifully.
Explain like a patient tutor talking to a nervous adult.
Write this in the voice of a friendly coach.
That is a style instruction wearing a costume, and style is exactly what personas are good at.
But when the job is a fact or a number, drop the costume and add honesty instead.
Look at the tax example.
The before version invites a confident wrong number delivered in an expert voice,
which is the most dangerous kind of wrong.
The after version asks plainly and invites the model to flag uncertainty.
Facts want plain questions.
Style wants personas.
That distinction alone puts you ahead of most of the internet.
Module three, and it is a short one with a big payoff.
You now know how to describe what you want.
But there is something even stronger than describing, and every professional prompt you will ever see uses it.
Show it.
First, the diagnosis.
You have seen the AI voice: delve, dive in, game-changer, I hope this email finds you well.
Why does everything come out sounding like that?
Because when you do not show the model what you want,
it writes the average of everything it has ever read,
and the average of the internet is exactly that beige, over-enthusiastic voice.
People try to fix it with adjectives: make it casual, make it punchy, make it warm.
Adjectives help a little.
But you and I might mean completely different things by casual.
A sample is unambiguous.
So here is the move.
Before you ask for the real thing, paste a short sample of the tone you want.
Here is an email I wrote that sounds like me.
Now write the new announcement in the same voice.
That is it.
One good sample usually transforms the output; two or three consistent ones lock it in.
And a detail that matters: the model imitates the pattern of whatever you show it, formatting included.
If your samples are tidy and consistent, the output will be too.
If they contradict each other, you get mush.
By the way, researchers call this few-shot prompting.
You can forget that name in ten seconds, as long as you keep the habit:
show before you ask.
The same show-don't-describe trick works for structure.
If you want a table, name the columns.
If you want a list, say how many items and what each line contains.
And when the shape is unusual, sketch one line of it.
Format each item like: name, year in parentheses, then a one-line why.
That single sketched line does more than a paragraph of description,
because the model completes patterns for a living, and you just handed it the pattern.
Task, context, format, and now a sample.
Your asks are already better than ninety percent of what these models see all day.
Next up: the steering habits that keep answers honest.
Module four.
Everything so far happens before you press enter.
This module is about steering: four small habits that change what comes back,
and what you do the moment it arrives.
None of them takes more than one sentence to use.
All of them will still work years from now, whatever the models are called by then.
Habit one.
Do not think of a pink elephant.
You just did, and so does the model.
When your instructions are a pile of don'ts, don't be formal, don't use jargon, don't make it long,
you are filling the model's attention with the exact things you want gone, and they leak back in.
The fix is to say what you want instead.
Write like you would text a friendly coworker.
Use everyday words.
Keep it under a hundred words.
Now, don'ts are not banned.
If the model keeps making one specific mistake, calling it out directly is fine.
Just pair every don't with a do, so the model always has somewhere to go,
not only somewhere to avoid.
Habit two, and if you only keep one line from this entire course, make it this one.
These models are trained to be helpful, and to their training, an empty answer feels like a failure.
So when they hit a gap, the pull is to fill it fluently,
which is exactly how you get a confident wrong answer.
You can push back with a single sentence.
If you're not fully sure, say so, and tell me what you'd check.
That is the whole habit.
It gives the model explicit permission to be uncertain,
and in practice it turns silent guesses into visible ones:
you get "I believe it's X but verify the current figure" instead of a smooth wrong number.
I use it on anything involving names, dates, prices, laws, or medicine.
Say it with me once: if you're not fully sure, say so, and tell me what you'd check.
Habit three is about the second most famous magic phrase: think step by step.
In 2023 it genuinely boosted accuracy.
Then models changed.
Researchers at Wharton tested it properly and found that on thinking models,
the ones that already reason privately before answering,
the phrase adds twenty to eighty percent more waiting for little or no accuracy gain.
You are telling someone who is already deep in thought to please think.
On instant models it still helps modestly with genuinely multi-step problems, but it also makes answers more variable,
so it can even break questions the model would have gotten right.
Here is the rule that survives: ask for steps when the task naturally has steps, a plan,
a checklist, a comparison.
And if the problem is truly hard, do not chant at the instant model.
Flip the switch from Module 1 and use the thinking mode.
That is what it is for.
Habit four, the biggest single productivity unlock for beginners.
Most people treat a chatbot like a slot machine: pull the lever once, take whatever falls out.
But the first answer is a first draft, and unlike a human intern,
this one revises instantly and never gets tired of your notes.
My three favorite follow-ups.
What's weak about this?
Fix it.
The model is surprisingly good at criticizing its own work when you ask.
Give me three versions: safe, bold, unexpected, so you choose instead of settle.
And my favorite, flipped around: ask me three questions before you answer,
which is wonderful whenever you are not sure what context the model needs.
One more pull of the lever is not failure.
It is the technique.
Here is your pocket toolkit, the second screenshot slide of the course.
Six moves.
Give it a job, not a topic.
Brief it with the context it cannot guess.
Show a sample.
Phrase things positively.
Give it an out.
And never ship the first draft.
Notice what is not on this list: no magic words, no personas for facts,
no chanting step by step at a model that is already thinking.
This list will still be true when the model names have changed five more times.
Take the screenshot, and then let's talk about something most people never learn at all:
how to work with your own material.
Module five.
So far we have worked inside one message box.
But the biggest quality jump available to you is not a better sentence.
It is better material.
What the model can see, your documents, your notes, your past chats,
decides what it can actually do for you.
The pros call this context engineering.
You can just call it handing over the folder.
First, the idea that clears up the most confusion.
When you upload a file to a chatbot, you are not teaching the AI.
Nothing about the model's brain changes,
and your file does not become part of some public pool of knowledge.
What you are doing is handing the intern a folder:
an open-book reference it can read for this conversation and, in the workspaces I will show you next,
for every conversation in that workspace.
That is why uploading beats summarizing your document by hand into the prompt box.
The model quotes your actual material instead of guessing.
One separate note while we are here:
whether your chats may be used to improve models is a privacy setting, not an upload side effect,
and every major app now lets you turn it off.
Worth checking once in settings.
All three big apps now give you a room where your material lives,
so you stop re-uploading and re-explaining.
In Claude they are called Projects: files plus standing instructions, shared by every chat inside.
ChatGPT has Projects too, same idea, plus Custom GPTs,
which are more like a packaged assistant you can hand to other people.
And Gemini has Gems, with a genuinely nice trick:
they can link to Google Drive files and stay current when the file changes.
Set one up this week.
Put in the three documents you reference constantly and one paragraph of standing instructions, who you are,
what you are working on, how you like answers.
It takes ten minutes, and it upgrades every single future chat.
File limits and names change often enough that I will not quote numbers;
the room is the durable idea.
Now a quirk that will save you real frustration.
When you give a model a lot of material, it does not weigh every page equally.
It is most reliable with what sits at the start and at the end,
and weakest in the middle.
Researchers literally call the effect lost in the middle.
So work with it.
Put your most important document, or your actual instruction, first or last,
never sandwiched in the middle of a giant paste.
When you do paste something huge, add a pointer: focus on section four, or,
the part I care about is the pricing table.
Big context windows are wonderful, but attention is not evenly spread,
and now you know where the strong seats are.
Last idea in this module, and it is one many daily users have never checked.
In 2026, the big chatbots remember things about you across separate chats: your job, your preferences,
your ongoing projects.
Used well, it is lovely, less re-explaining.
But you should know three things.
First, you can read everything it has stored: in ChatGPT under Settings, Personalization, Memory; in Claude under Settings,
Memory; in Gemini on the Saved info page.
Second, you can edit or delete any of it, and memories do go stale,
so glance at the list occasionally, the way you would clean out a junk drawer.
And third, every app now has a temporary or incognito chat mode that leaves no memory behind,
for the conversations you want to stay in the room.
The AI keeping notes on you is fine.
Not knowing it keeps notes is not.
Last module, and the one I most want you to keep.
You can now get impressive answers on demand.
This module is about the moment right after, when you decide what to do with one.
Because the difference between people who get real value from AI
and people who get burned by it is rarely the prompting.
It is the judgment.
Start with the uncomfortable fact from Course 1, now with 2026 numbers.
These models sometimes generate confident, fluent, specific answers that are simply wrong.
Stanford's AI Index this year measured hallucination rates across twenty-six top models on one
benchmark and found them ranging from twenty-two percent all the way to ninety-four percent,
depending on the model and task.
The detail that matters for you: the tone never wobbles.
A wrong answer sounds exactly like a right one, polished, structured, sure of itself.
So do not use confidence as your signal, ever.
Use cost.
If a wrong answer costs you nothing, a movie recommendation, enjoy.
If it costs money, health, a grade, or your reputation, you verify.
Here is how, in about sixty seconds.
The verification move is called lateral reading, and it is what professional fact-checkers do.
Do not sit inside the chat asking, are you sure?
The model will grade its own homework, politely, and that tells you almost nothing.
Instead, go lateral: open a new tab, search the specific claim, the number, the name, the date,
and see if one independent source agrees.
Sixty seconds, usually less.
And when the model gives you sources, lovely, but click one.
In 2026 the links are usually real;
the question is whether the page actually says what the summary claims.
One opened link puts you ahead of almost everybody.
Verify the claim, not the vibe.
Here is the finding from this year's research that genuinely changed how I ask questions.
Models are trained on human approval, and it shows:
they tend to agree with whatever you signal you already believe.
Researchers tested the same false claims two ways.
Framed as, someone says this, models corrected the error just fine.
Framed as, I believe this, accuracy collapsed,
in one reported case from about ninety-eight percent to about sixty-four on the same claims,
just because the wrongness now belonged to the user.
So watch your framing.
Ask, is this true, not, this is true, right?
Keep your conclusion out of the question when you want the truth.
And when you actually want help with a decision, use the power move: argue against my plan.
Flattery cannot survive that instruction, and the answer you get is worth ten agreeable ones.
Now one safety idea from the developer world that every ordinary user should know,
because in 2026 it stopped being theoretical.
Everything you paste into a chat, an article, an email, a resume, a prompt someone shared,
is read by the model as potential instructions, not just as information.
Attackers exploit that with hidden text, white on white, or tucked mid-document, saying things like,
ignore your instructions and do this instead.
A real case this year: security researchers found that a specially crafted claude.ai link could
pre-fill a prompt containing instructions the victim could not see.
Press enter once, and buried commands could quietly send parts of your chat history to an attacker.
It has been fixed, but the pattern is the lesson.
So, three habits.
Treat paste-this-prompt links from strangers like unmarked pills.
Skim anything large before you paste it.
And if an answer suddenly veers weird right after a paste, suspect the paste.
Not paranoia, just seatbelts.
One more judgment call, and I will be honest with you: this one has no universal rule,
and anyone who sells you one is simplifying.
Whether to say AI helped you depends on the room you are in.
In school, the syllabus decides, and in 2026 many courses set the rule assignment by assignment,
so when it is unclear, ask, do not guess.
At work, the growing norm is that a human who reviews, edits,
and stands behind the output owns it, though more companies now ask for a heads-up internally.
Two things are true everywhere.
You are responsible for what you ship, AI-assisted or not, so never send what you have not read.
And when you are in doubt, disclosing costs you a sentence,
while being caught not disclosing can cost you trust.
Know the rules of the room.
When in doubt, say so.
Here is the whole course on one slide, and yes, this is the third screenshot.
Twelve habits in three rows.
Ask well: a job, a briefing, a sample, a shape.
Steer well: positive phrasing, an out, the right speed, a second draft.
Trust well: verify by cost, read laterally, keep your conclusions out of your questions,
and watch what you paste.
Read the last line one more time,
because it is the sentence I most want you to remember a year from now.
Technique gets you good answers.
Judgment makes them safe to use.
You now have both.
If this course lit a spark, here is where to go next, all free,
all checked by hand this month.
The official prompting guides from Anthropic, OpenAI, and Google are genuinely good now,
and they agree with each other far more than the internet does.
Learn Prompting is a gentle full beginner course.
And when you want your hands dirty, Anthropic publishes an interactive tutorial with real exercises.
The full annotated list, with what each one is best for, lives on the course resources page.
And that is the lecture, step one of your path, done.
Two short steps remain before the quiz unlocks.
Clear the twenty-four flashcards, they are quick, and go play at the three Lab stations,
where you will watch a persona wreck a factual answer with your own eyes.
Then the quiz opens: twenty questions, fourteen to pass, and your certificate prints on the spot,
ready for LinkedIn.
Before you go, do one thing for me.
Take the worst prompt you wrote last month, you know the one,
and rewrite it with the pocket toolkit.
Send both versions to a friend who needs this course.
That is the whole final exam of real life: better asks, wiser trust.
A new Cambium Academy course lands next week.
I will see you there.